Benjamin Edwards Green papers, Inclusive: 1840-1865
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Benjamin Edwards Green papers
Inclusive: 1840-1865
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3830
Green, Benjamin Edwards, 1822 - 1907
2 document boxes
The Benjamin Edwards Green papers consists of a postcard, pamphlets, written notes, an unpublished manuscript and other chapter fragments. There is also a written genealogy of the Green family.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
Benjamin Edwards Green was born in Elkton, Kentucky, on 1822 February 12, to Lucretia Marie Edwards and Duff Green. Benjamin's father, Duff, was an influential newspaper editor, diplomat, industrialist, and friend of Abraham Lincoln. Benjamin grew up in Washington D.C., surrounded by men with political influence and diplomatic connections. He attended Georgetown College and graduated in 1838, then turning his attentions to obtaining a law degree from the University of Virginia. Green finally settled in New Orleans to practice law.
In 1843, politician John C. Calhoun was influential in securing a post for Benjamin as Secretary of the Legation to Mexico, where he served as the charge d’affaires at the Mexican capitol from 1843-1845, during the period leading up to the Mexican-American War. He had the authority to negotiate for the United States on border disputes between Mexico and Pre-Republic Texas, and after the War, was hired by Mexico to organize indemnity payments to U.S. citizens.
After serving as a diplomat to Mexico, Green returned to Washington D.C. in 1845 and began writing for newspapers on political issues and practicing law. He also became heavily involved with his father in many business endeavors. In 1849, Green was sent by President Zachary Taylor to the West Indies to negotiate for a naval station with the Dominican Republic. He also was to secretly attempt to ascertain the depth of support and influence of Spain and France in the region and look into the purchase of Cuba by the U.S. government.
Green returned to the U.S. In the 1850s, and again joined with his father in numerous developments in the United States that would promote industrial growth and the addition of railroads in the South. He became solicitor and general manager of the American Industrial Agency, an organization that was established to attract northern and European investments, and continually worked to promote the financial and economic growth of the South. It is unclear whether Green served in the Civil War, but with his father taking neither side in the slavery/secessionist conflict, it is highly likely that Green, too, was of the same mind. His saw slavery as a capitalism-labor issue and that the conflict between the two was “the greatest and most difficult problem of modern civilizationELleading to four years of fratricide between the states.”
Benjamin E. Green died at the age of 85 after a brief illness, at his home in Dalton, Georgia. He was survived by his wife, Lizzie, two daughters and one son.
Scope and Content
The Benjamin Edwards Green papers consist of Green's unpublished manuscript, Reminiscences, unpublished manuscript fragments, two pamphlets, notes, a postcard, and a family genealogy tracing the Green family back to George Washington. Green's unpublished manuscript is the largest section of the Papers, though it was advertised as "coming soon." It is perhaps the most interesting document in the collection and not only provides Green's views on the times as he saw them, but also presents his view on the Civil War, slavery, and its causes. His role as a secret agent to the West Indies is also related in the manuscript. The manuscript fragments are not parts of the main manuscript but seem to be parts of other numbered chapters of other publications, either published or unpublished.
Arrangement
The Benjamin Edwards Green papers were partially organized when they arrived and this partial arrangement was kept when possible. The entire collection is housed in sheet-protectors due to its poor condition. There are pages of the unpublished manuscript missing so the page numbering is not always consecutive.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3830. Acquired 2012-11-09
Related Resources
Related finding aids
Duff Green Papers #993, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill.
Related references
"Col. Ben E. Green." Bartow County GenWeb. Accessed 2013 April 30.
Michael Brown Rare Books, LLC. "List #118: Recent Acquisitions of Manuscript Americana." Philadelphia, PA: 2012.
Schoonover, Thomas. "Green, Benjamin Edwards." American National Biography Online. Accessed 2013 May 21.
Cowan's Auctions, Inc. "Ben E. Green, Politician & Colonel, Unpublished, Handwritten Memoirs & Related Ephemera, 2012 June 21." Accessed 2013 May 21.
Duff Green Papers, Accession #993, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Green, Benjamin Edwards
Places
Dominican Republic.; Texas -- History.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects
Genealogy.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Slavery -- America.
Genres
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Pamphlets.
- Correspondence, 1907, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of one postcard from the Memorial Department and three pages of handwritten notes.
  - Correspondence: Postcard & Notes, 1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Literary Productions, 1900-circa 1908, undated; 2
  This series consists of one unpublished manuscript written by Green, two pamphlets, six pieces of unidentified manuscript fragments, and one postscript on State Old Age Pensions.
  - Literary Productions: Pamphlets, "Shakespeare and Goethe, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Literary Productions: Pamphlets: "Dalton Real Estate Pool", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 1, pgs. 1-25, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 1, pgs. 26-52, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 2, pgs, 53, 55-65, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 3, pgs. 66-81, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 3, pgs. 82-99, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 4, pgs. 101-124, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 4, pgs. 125-145, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 5, pgs. 146-156, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 6, pgs. 160-188, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 7, pgs. 189-215, circa 1908 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 7, pgs. 216-240, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscripts: "Reminiscences," Chapter 7, pgs. 241-264, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 8, pgs. 265-280, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 8, pgs. 299-321, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 9, pgs. 322-350, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscript: "Reminiscences," Chapter 10, pgs. 351-364, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions: Unpublished Manuscripts: "Reminiscences," Chapter 11, pgs. 371-405, circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragments, 3 pages, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragement, pg. 4, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragment, Chapter 45, pgs. 346-361, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragment, Chapter 46, pgs. 362-371, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragment, Chapter 49, pgs. 394-399, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragment, Chapter "X3," pgs. 1-6 & Chapter 25 Summary, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Literary Productions: Unidentified Manuscript Fragment: Postcirpt, "State Old Age Pensions," pgs. 21-23, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Genealogy, 1907, undated; 3
  This series contains genealogical information relating to the Green family. One is a write-up on the Green Family as related to George Washington. Also included is a write-up on the family of General Duff Green (Benjamin's Father), and a copy of a newspaper obituary on Ben E. Green.
  - Genealogy: Family Tree and Obituary, 1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)